<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Vishwath Mohan]]></title>
  <link href="http://vishwathmohan.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://vishwathmohan.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-05-02T22:03:58-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://vishwathmohan.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Vishwath Mohan]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Blog Setup]]></title>
    <link href="http://vishwathmohan.com/blog/2013/04/30/my-blog-setup/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-30T23:36:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://vishwathmohan.com/blog/2013/04/30/my-blog-setup</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;m obsessive to a fault when it comes to researching the right tool
for a job. I could (and do) spend days sifting through article
after article comparing different languages, libraries, programming
paradigms, every little thing you could imagine every time I start a
new project. It&#8217;s actually one of the reasons I have so many
incomplete projects on my hands.</p>

<h3>The Search</h3>

<p>Naturally, picking a blog engine to use was no exception. I used a
small checklist of features for comparison as I looked around. Here
they are in no particular order -</p>

<!-- more -->


<ul>
<li><p>As a programmer I was looking for something that didn&#8217;t deviate too
far from a coding workflow (which is a fancy way of saying &#8220;me want
emacs&#8221;).</p></li>
<li><p>As a security researcher I obviously prefered a solution that was as
secure as possible.</p></li>
<li><p>As a lazy person, I wanted something that would be both functional
and aesthetically sensible out of the box (or with minimal setup).</p></li>
<li><p>I didn&#8217;t need an overwhelming set of features, so simplicity (both
of use and design) was preferable.</p></li>
<li><p>I wanted to be able to go under the hood to make my own
customizations if I wanted to. But more than that, I wanted to be
able to look at the source and really understand what was going
on. This is obviously harder that larger the code base gets, and so
is somewhat related to the previous point. It&#8217;s also related to the
next two points.</p></li>
<li><p>If it catered to my irrational dislike and ignorance of PHP, then
all the better (I really need to sit down and go beyond the hello
world stuff with PHP at some point. Hopefully that point is very,
very far away).</p></li>
<li><p>If it catered to my irrational (it&#8217;s not irrational really, I only
say this out of a sense of fairness to the point above) love and
appreciation of Python, Ruby, or Lisp then all the better.</p></li>
</ul>


<h3>Octopress is awesome</h3>

<p>I picked <a href="https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll">Jekyll</a> initially, which
is more blog generator than blog engine. It takes a configuration
file, your posts and pages written in markdown and uses them to
generate (people also call it baking) an almost entirely static blog.</p>

<p>Eventually though, I settled with
<a href="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</a>&#8212;an extra layer over Jeyll that
manages to add just enough to hit that sweet spot between features and
ease of use. It integrates easily with Twitter, Google Analytics and
other useful services, it also integrates with comment systems like
Disqus (which to be fair, Jekyll does too), and has options to easily
deploy to <a href="http://pages.github.com/">Github Pages</a>,
<a href="https://www.heroku.com/">Heroku</a> or any rsync enabled hosting
service. I really like how well Octopress manages to cover every
single point in my checklist -</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Octopress allows me to write my posts locally using my editor of
choice (*<em>cough</em>*Emacs*<em>cough</em>*), and makes it trivial to save,
generate and deploy the generated site.</p></li>
<li><p>Jekyll (and consequently Octopress) uses git to manage both the
markdown source and the generated site, making it easy to work
across mulitple machines and still keep things synchronized.</p></li>
<li><p>You can&#8217;t get more secure than an entirely (almost) static
site. Well, technically you could not have a site at all and be
more secure. But practically, a baked blog is about as exploit free
as you could get.</p></li>
<li><p>Assuming you have Git and Ruby installed on your machine already,
you can have a blog up and running in literally a few minutes. The
Octopress site does a great job of explaining how to <a href="http://octopress.org/docs/setup/">install and
configure</a> it to your liking.</p>

<p>I switched my theme to
<a href="http://panks.me/blog/2013/01/new-octopress-theme-fabric/">Fabric</a>&#8212;which
I&#8217;m using as is simply because of how much I love it&#8212;but it
wasn&#8217;t because of any shortcomings with the default theme, which
looks just great.</p></li>
<li><p>The source for both Jekyll and Octopress is simple, well-written,
and easy to read. It certainly doesn&#8217;t hurt that they&#8217;re both
implemented in Ruby.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>I&#8217;m currently hosting the blog on Github Pages, which seemed like a
good starting point. I don&#8217;t have comments enabled at the moment,
which might seem like a controversial choice. I happened to read through
<a href="http://mattgemmell.com/">Matt Gemmel&#8217;s</a> excellent chronicling of his
decision to disable comments recently, (you can read his first post on it
<a href="http://mattgemmell.com/2011/11/29/comments-off/">here</a>, and the
bottom of that page contains links to his follow-ups) and agree more
or less with what he has to say.</p>

<p>As it stands I don&#8217;t really expect a vast readership, but if you have
something to say about anything I post, I&#8217;d be glad for you to give me
a shout out on <a href="https://twitter.com/vishwath">Twitter</a> or by
<a href="mailto:vishwath.mohan@gmail.com">mail</a>, both of which seem like more
natural mediums to carry out a discussion.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Here I am]]></title>
    <link href="http://vishwathmohan.com/blog/2013/04/30/so-here-i-am/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-30T21:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://vishwathmohan.com/blog/2013/04/30/so-here-i-am</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;ve been meaning to blog for some time now, having a vague sense that
it would be beneficial but never really sitting down to examine it
more closely. I did just that today though, and realized that there
are so many good reasons for me to maintain one there was no point in
delaying it any longer. It seemed natural to begin by listing the top
3 things I&#8217;m expecting blogging will help me with.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h4>1. Complete what I begin</h4>

<p>Often, when I&#8217;m working on a new project, I&#8217;m sorely tempted to go
online in an attempt to better educate myself about what&#8217;s already
been done. A few hours and many links later, I&#8217;ve found something else
that interests me so much that I drop what I was working on to attempt
that instead.</p>

<p>In some ways its a consequence of an entirely good thing&#8212;a sense of
fascination for the things I encounter. What I really need is
something to force my attention back to what I&#8217;ve started so I can see
them through to completion. Writing publicly about each new thing I
begin will go a long way towards that (that&#8217;s the hope at any rate).</p>

<h4>2. Remember what I read</h4>

<p>I suffer from a mild case of information addiction. Now I don&#8217;t
feel the compulsive need to check social networks or email. I&#8217;m even
fairly sure that my Facebook login frequency is firmly in the
offend-my-friends zone. My information drug of choice happens to be
rss feeds (Quora comes a close second), and I&#8217;ve found that I can spend
the entire day skipping from one fascinating article to the next.</p>

<p>This wouldn&#8217;t be so bad if I didn&#8217;t have an entirely lousy memory.
Currently, I forget a lot of what I come across and am little better
off than not having read it at all. I might even be worse off for any
induced
<a href="http://psychcentral.com/blog/archives/2013/01/21/overcoming-information-overload/">cognitive overload</a>.</p>

<p>I&#8217;ve decided that the best way to make this work for me is to attempt
writing about (even a fraction of) the things I read. Writing is a
useful device to improve both retention and recall, and although
typing isn&#8217;t quite as effective as putting
<a href="http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052748704631504575531932754922518.html">pen to paper</a>,
its sure to help me remember more of what I read. More importantly,
forcing my ideas onto (virtual) paper will afford me the opportunity
to recognize connections between seemingly disparate ideas and place
them into a larger, richer perspective of the world.</p>

<h4>3. Improve as a person</h4>

<p>Finally, writing in of itself is a great habit to cultivate. Leo
Babuta has a great <a href="http://zenhabits.net/write-daily/">article</a> that
explains the many good things that come from regular writing. The
reasons that really resonated with me were the ability to -</p>

<ol>
<li>Think from the perspective of people around you.</li>
<li>Improve the clarity and logical consistency of your thoughts and
opinions.</li>
<li>Reflect on your life and choices</li>
</ol>


<p>Individually, each of these traits are immensely beneficial. Together,
they transform you into a better, wiser person. And who wouldn&#8217;t want
that?</p>

<p>So&#8230;here I am!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
